Guide to the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Local 2090 Records WAG.120
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Local 2090 Records
1899, 1917-1987
1917-1963
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America. Local 246 (Norfolk, Conn.)
United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America. Local 2090 (New York, N.Y.)
United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America. Local 2155
United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America. Local 1164
Alongi, Vincent
WAG.120
7.5 Linear Feet in 7 record cartons, one manuscript box, and 3 legal-size folders.
The United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Local 2090 of New York City was created in 1918 and disbanded in 1944. Between 1937 and 1940, Local 2090 was involved in a dispute with the national union and legal proceedings regarding amendments to the general constitution of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, the revocation of Local 2090's charter, and its reinstatement by the New York Supreme Court. The collection dates between 1899 and 1987, with the bulk dating between 1917 and 1963, and consists of the records of Local 2090 and locals with which it merged, including Locals 1164, 2155, and 246. Materials include minute books, financial and membership ledgers, court documents, union newsletters and fliers, membership cards, and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restriction.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
The container list is organized in chronological order by union local number and in alphabetical order by format of material under each union local.
Historical Note
The United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Local 2090 of New York City was created in 1918 and disbanded in 1944. Between 1937 and 1940, Local 2090 was involved in a dispute with the national union and legal proceedings regarding amendments to the general constitution of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, the revocation of Local 2090's charter, and its reinstatement by the New York Supreme Court. After the General Convention of 1936, Local 2090 led a campaign in opposition to amendments to the general constitution specifically directed at the Communist Party. In early 1938, the local published and widely circulated a pamphlet stating their case, and its charter was subsequently revoked on grounds that this activity violated one of the new amendments. Local 2090 filed a legal suit in civil court and were ultimately victorious. The legal process took several years, during which time the local's membership steadily decreased. In 1944 it was disbanded and replaced by Local 2155.
Scope and Contents
The collection dates between 1899 and 1987, with the bulk dating between 1917 and 1963, and consists of the records of Local 2090 and locals with which it merged, including Locals 1164, 2155, and 246. Materials include minute books, financial and membership ledgers, court documents, union newsletters and fliers, membership cards, and photographs. The bulk of the collection consists of minute books documenting general membership meetings of Local 2090 and membership ledgers of Local 1164. The collection includes court documents and newsletters and fliers from Local 2090 documenting their dispute with the national union and the legal case regarding the revocation of Local 2090's charter. Also included are dues books from Austria, Germany, Israel, the Netherlands, Norway, and Sweden, which were transferred into Local 1164 by new members immigrating to the United States from those countries.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Alongi Vincent on behalf of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Local 2090, in 2000. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1999.016 and 1999.017.
Materials found in the repository were added to the collection. The accession number associated with this material is 2018.004.
The accession number NPA 1995.021 is also associated with this collection.
Building trades -- New York (State) -- New York; Building trades -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States.; Carpenters -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America. Local 2090 (New York, N.Y.); Alongi, Vincent
- Local 246 -- Photograph, undated (Box Shared Tamiment A004)
- Local 1164 -- By-laws, membership and dues books, apprentice book, 1922-1955 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Local 1164 -- Dues ledger, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Local 1164 -- Executive Board minute book, 1927-1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Local 1164 -- Financial ledgers, 1943-1963 (Box 3, Volume 1-4)
- Local 1164 -- Financial ledger, 1977-1987 (Box 6, Volume 3)
- Local 1164 -- Foreign dues books, 1899, 1943-1956 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
- Local 1164 -- Membership ledgers, 1924-1939 (Box 2, Volume 1-3)
- Local 1164 -- Membership ledgers, 1926-1931 (Box 5, Volume 1-2)
- Local 1164 -- Membership ledgers, 1928-1929, 1940-1945 (Box 4, Volume 1-3)
- Local 1164 -- Membership ledgers, 1942-1947 (Box 6, Volume 1-2)
- Local 1164 -- Minute books, 1917-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1-7, Folder 10)
- Local 2090 -- Meeting transcript, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Local 2090 -- Minute books, 1918-1937 (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
- Local 2090 -- Minute books, 1921-1944 (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
- Local 2090 -- New York Supreme Court of Appeals documents, 1938 (Box 7, Folder 5-7)
- Local 2090 -- Photographs, undated (Box Shared Tamiment A004)
- Local 2090 -- Union newsletters and fliers, court documents, correspondence, and clippings, 1934-1942 (Box 7, Folder 10-12)
- Locals 2090 and 2155 -- Defense Fund ledger, 1940-1960 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Local 2155 -- Clippings, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Local 2155 -- Photographs, undated (Box Shared Tamiment A004)
- Local 2155 and Local 246 banners, undated (Box 9)